Johannes Nicolaus Wibisana

PHD STUDENT

Onna-son, Okinawa, Japan

【 (+81) 50-3707-5757 | ☑ johannes.nicolaus@oist.jp | ★ www.jnicolaus.com | ☑ johannesnicolaus | ☒ johannes-nicolaus | ☒ JN Wibisana

Summary

I am a 3rd year PhD student at the Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology at the Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit. I am currently working to investigate the gene regulation of the scrambled genome of *Oikopleura dioica*. Previously, I have used single-cell omics and fluorescence imaging analysis to investigate NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell. I am familiar with R, ImageJ macro and bash programming languages for image processing and analysis of multi-omics data. I also have experience with basic molecular biology experiments such as mammalian and avian cell culture, RNA-FISH, molecular cloning, genome editing and qPCR. Being highly adaptable and proactive, I am keen and can quickly grasp new concepts that can be applied to my current and future research.

Education

Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology

Okinawa, Japan

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY Apr. 2022 - Present

- Epigenetic landscape in the cryptic species of Oikopleura dioica. Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit (Pl: Nicholas Luscombe)
- Rotation projects:
 Investigation of dental microwear analysis in fish-tetrapod transition. Macroevolution Unit (PI: Lauren Sallan)

 Investigation of metabolic-related gene duplication in pomacentridae. Marine Eco-Evo-Devo Unit (PI: Vincent Laudet)

Osaka University (Graduate School of Science)

Osaka, Japan

M.S.C IN BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES Apr. 2020 - Mar. 2022

- Thesis research: NF-kB transcriptional regulation in B-cell, Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada)
- Awardee of the Honjo International Scholarship Foundation scholarship
- · Others: In charge of laboratory website and bioinformatics training of visiting researchers

Osaka University (Graduate School of Science)

Osaka, Japan

B.SC IN BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES Oct. 2016 - Mar. 2020

- Thesis research: NF-kB transcriptional regulation in B-cell, Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada)
- Awardee of the MEXT scholarship
- Selected for the AEARU 2018 Summer Camp in Hefei China
- Qualified for early graduation

Publications

RESEARCH ARTICLES

The complete mitogenome of an unidentified Oikopleura species

F1000Research

JN WIBISANA, C PLESSY*, N DIERCXKSENS, J MIAO, NM LUSCOMBE

2024

Modifiable clinical dental impression methods to obtain whole-mouth and detailed dental traits from vertebrates

Journal of Morphology

JN WIBISANA*, RA SALLAN*, T OTA, P PUCHENKOV, T KUBO, L SALLAN*

2024

Type 2 helper T cells convert into Interleukin-13-expressing follicular helper T cells after antigen repriming

Translational and Regulatory
Sciences

Y Harada, T Sasaki, **JN Wibisana**, M Okada, C Liu, H Ueno, PD Burrows, M Kubo*

2022

2022

Enhanced transcriptional heterogeneity mediated by NF-кВ super-enhancers

PLoS Genetics

JN Wibisana, T Inaba, H Shinohara, N Yumoto, T Hayashi, M Umeda, M Ebisawa, I Nikaido, Y Sako, M Okada*

form ation

ASURAT: functional annotation-driven unsupervised clustering of single-cell

Bioinformatics

K IIDA*, J KONDO, **JN WIBISANA**, M INOUE, M OKADA

2022

REVIEW ARTICLES

Encoding and decoding NF-кВ nuclear dynamics

JN WIBISANA, M OKADA*

Current Opinion in Cell Biology

2022

Prediction of transcriptional regulation in immune cells through single-cell analysis

Journal of Clinical and Experimental

Medicine (Igaku no Ayumi)

JN WIBISANA, K IIDA, M OKADA

Presentations

INTERNATIONAL

Gene regulation of the scrambled genome of Oikopleura dioica

EMBO LECTURE COURSE: EVOLUTIONARY AND COMPARATIVE GENOMICS (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Epigenetic landscape of the cryptic tunicate Oikopleura dioica

EMBO Workshop: Animal Genomes (Poster presentation)

Imaging and single-cell sequencing analysis of super-enhancer activation mediated by NF-κB in B cells

CELL SYMPOSIA: BIOLOGICAL ASSEMBLIES - PHASE TRANSITIONS AND MORE (POSTER PRESENTATION)

NF-kB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

COLD Spring Harbor Laboratory Biology of Genomes 2021 (Poster presentation)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

JAPAN-KOREA BILATERAL SYMPOSIUM BETWEEN IPR AND SNU ON ADVANCED ANALYSIS OF PROTEIN FUNCTION AND

STRUCTURE (ORAL PRESENTATION)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE OF SYSTEMS BIOLOGY (POSTER PRESENTATION)

DOMESTIC

Enhancer-mediated transcriptional regulation in Oikopleura dioica

THE 46TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE MOLECULAR BIOLOGY SOCIETY OF JAPAN (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Enhancer-mediated transcriptional regulation in Oikopleura dioica

THE 45TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE MOLECULAR BIOLOGY SOCIETY OF JAPAN (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Imaging and single-cell sequencing analysis of super-enhancer activation mediated by

NF-kB in B cells

19TH IPR RETREAT (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Imaging and single-cell sequencing analysis of super-enhancer activation mediated by

NF-κB in B cells

CELL SYMPOSIA: BIOLOGICAL ASSEMBLIES - PHASE TRANSITIONS AND MORE (POSTER PRESENTATION)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

COLD Spring Harbor Laboratory Biology of Genomes 2021 (Poster presentation)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

THE 58TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE BIOPHYSICAL SOCIETY OF JAPAN (POSTER PRESENTATION)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

JAPAN-KOREA BILATERAL SYMPOSIUM BETWEEN IPR AND SNU ON ADVANCED ANALYSIS OF PROTEIN FUNCTION AND

STRUCTURE (ORAL PRESENTATION)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

18TH IPR RETREAT (ORAL PRESENTATION)

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE OF SYSTEMS BIOLOGY (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Research Experience

Nafplio, Greece

Nov. 2024

Sevilla, Spain

Nov. 2021

Online

Nov. 2021

Online

May 2021

Seoul, South Korea

Jan. 2020

Okinawa, Japan

Nov. 2019

Fukuoka, Japan

Nov 2024

Chiba, Japan

Nov. 2022

Online

Nov 2021

Online

Nov. 2021

Online

May 2021

Online

Sep. 2020

Seoul, South Korea

Jan. 2020

Osaka, Japan

Nov. 2019

Okinawa, Japan

Nov. 2019

Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit (PI: Nicholas Luscombe), Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology

Okinawa, Japan Mar. 2022 - Present

• Project: Epigenetic landscape in the cryptic species O. dioica

- Analysis of RNA-seq, ATAC-seq, CAGE, and other epigenetic sequencing data
- Improved genome annotation of O. dioica
- Developed a genome browser for O. dioica: oikobrowser.jnicolaus.com

Macroevolution Unit (PI: Lauren Sallan), Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology

Okinawa, Japan

PhD Rotation student

PHD STUDENT

- Project: Investigation of dental microwear analysis in fish-tetrapod transition
- Established fish facility for Polypterus
- Performed dental molding of fossils and subsequent scanning using confocal microscope

Marine Eco-Evo-Devo Unit (PI: Vincent Laudet), Okinawa Institute of Science and **Technology**

Okinawa, Japan

PhD Rotation student

• Project: Investigation of metabolic gene duplication in clownfish

- Performed gene duplication analysis using computational phylogenetic analysis
- Performed fish dissection for RNA extraction and subsequent qPCR analysis

Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

Feb. 2019 - Mar. 2022

UNDERGRADUATE - MASTER'S STUDENT

- Project: NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell
- Performed quantitative imaging analysis of NF-кВ nuclear translocation using confocal microscope and ImageJ
- Performed single-cell RNA-seq and single-cell ATAC-seq analysis to find the relationship between cis-regulatory elements and gene expression
- Performed single-molecule RNA-FISH and qPCR for the confirmation of RNA-seq results
- Performed cloning for both transient and permanent expression of fluorescent-tagged protein of interest
- In charge of side projects concerning RNA-seq analysis and training of visiting researchers on RNA-seq analysis

Laboratory of Science and Innovation for Pain, Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Apr. 2018 - Feb. 2019

- Performed mouse genotyping, RNA extraction and ELISA
- Performed image analysis of mouse MRI images
- In charge of laboratory cleanliness

Bio Medical Wet Robotics Laboratory (PI: Morishima Keisuke), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

2017-2018

- ASSOCIATE PROJECT LEADER FOR OSAKA UNIVERSITY BIOMOD 2017-2018
- · Performed basic DNA origami experiments
- Performed 3D modeling and computer simulated DNA origami design

Laboratory of Cellular Life Science (PI: Naotada Ishihara), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

Sep. 2018 - Feb. 2019

RESEARCH INTERN

Project: Quantification of Mitochondrial Morphology

- Performed quantitative analysis of mitochondrial morphology using ImageJ
- · Performed basic experiments such as mammalian cell culture and confocal imaging

Honors & Awards.

Apr. 2020 - Honjo International Scholarship Foundation Scholarship

Japan

Mar. 2022

Sep. 2020 Poster presentation award, The 58th Annual meeting of the Biophysical Society of Japan

Japan

Bronze award, BIOMOD 2018 Molecular Design Competition

U.S.A

Bronze award, BIOMOD 2017 Molecular Design Competition

U.S.A

Sep. 2016 - MEXT scholarship

Japan

Mar. 2020

Workshops_

Dec. 2022 EMBO Practical Course: Single-cell omics: deeper to genomics

Heidelberg. Germany

Jul. 2020 第30回細胞生物学ワークショップ

Hyogo, Japan

Qualifications ____

Organizations _____

2019-2021 **Secretary General,** Indonesian Student Association in Japan 2018-2019 **President**, Indonesian Student Association in Japan (Osaka-Nara)

Other skills_

Web development HTML, CSS (Bootstrap), Jekyll, AWS.

3D printing and modeling Basic 3D modeling using Fusion360 and Maya. Familiar with basic 3D printing techniques.